<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Rabshakeh's outrage reproved, or, A VVhip for William Grigge of Bristoll, tanner to scourge him for his many notorious lies, blasphemies, reproaches, vain boastings and other such like noysom matter ... in a late fiery pamphlet ... entituled The Quakers Jesus ... / by an impartial friend to God's truth under what notion soever persecuted by the blind world.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28641</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11247928</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204995</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240942546</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R118</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11247928</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28641)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204995)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1449:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Rabshakeh's outrage reproved, or, A VVhip for William Grigge of Bristoll, tanner to scourge him for his many notorious lies, blasphemies, reproaches, vain boastings and other such like noysom matter ... in a late fiery pamphlet ... entituled The Quakers Jesus ... / by an impartial friend to God's truth under what notion soever persecuted by the blind world.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: print showthrough with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Errata at end of page 46.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Grigge, William. --  Quakers Jesus.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204995:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>RABSHAKEH'S OUTRAGE</hi> REPROVED. OR, A VVHIP FOR <hi>William Grigge</hi> of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> Tanner, <hi>To Scourge him,</hi> For his many notorious lies, blasphemies, reproaches, vain boastings, and other such like noysom matter, vomited out against the Truth and its Friends, in a late fiery Pamphlet, (published under his name) entituled, <hi>The Quakers Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Which, He hath proclaimed his own shame, and infamy, as in many other particulars, so more especially, by his most abominable hypocrisie, in charging that as matter of crime upon the men of his indignation, of which he himself is herein-after, proved to stand guilty by his own practise.</p>
            <p>By an impartial friend to God's Truth, under what notion soever persecuted by the Blind World.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke 6.45.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>An evil man out of the evil treasure of his heart, bringeth forth that which is evil; for of the abundance of the heart his mouth speaketh.</p>
            </q>
            <p>—<hi>E cantu dignoscitur Avis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> at the <hi>Black-Spread-Eagle</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t the West-End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:204995:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204995:2"/>
            <head>To the sober-minded unprejudic'd READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT's not my delight to be raking in that <hi>mire</hi> which the <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled Sea</hi> of any man's unclean spirit hath cast up. Yet where I find malice throwing it on the face of <hi>truth,</hi> or its <hi>friends,</hi> I can patiently bear the burden of its ill savour, whilest with the hand of <hi>love</hi> I wash it into the channel.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Grigg's</hi> design is, to asperse and render odious, (among others) that <hi>every-where-despised</hi> people called <hi>QUAKERS:</hi> his engines are <hi>lies, reproaches, mis-interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, false reports,</hi> and other such hellish materials, with which the <hi>Accuser of the brethren</hi> (his master) hath furnished him from out of the bottomlesse pitt. <hi>He hath</hi> lickt up <hi>Ralph Farmer's</hi> loathsome vomit, cast out in his last bundle of uncleannesse, upon the truth, and professors in all forms, that will not subject their necks to his feet, and disgorgeth himself thereof in his pamphlet upon the same persons. And the better to deceive the simply-credulous (if yet there be any so simple as to be deceived by him) he hath assum'd to himself the old Pharisai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Covering, by crying, <hi>The Temple of the Lord, Christ, Scriptures, Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. hoping to conceal the murderous <hi>Wolf</hi> that lodgeth in his brest, by creeping under the <hi>Lamb's</hi> skin; and to alloy the noysome smell of his inward rottennesse, by painting the Sepulchre.</p>
            <p>But his covering is too short, and his paint too thin; so that, notwithstanding his elder-like deportment through an affected
<pb facs="tcp:204995:3"/>gravity in speech, and manners; and his seeming godlinesse in profession of words, I shall so unmask him to every <hi>single eye,</hi> as that he will plainly be discerned to be a bitter enemy to the <hi>life</hi> of God wheresoever it appeareth, and his brest to be the bloody seat of <hi>rage,</hi> and <hi>violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not my purpose to trace him in all his wilde wanderings to and fro about the businesse of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> and his few fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers: he and they do stand or fall to their own Master.</p>
            <p>Onely to thee Reader I say, when thou seest another <hi>slip,</hi> let it learn thee (not to be <hi>high-minded,</hi> but) <hi>to fear,</hi> and look well to thy own footing; and when thou <hi>standest, take heed lest thou fall.</hi> Run not with the multitude, Conclude not of things pertaining to the Kingdom of God with the worldly wise; judge not of the <hi>tree by leaves,</hi> but by his <hi>fruits;</hi> Let not thy faith stand in the dictates of another, but <hi>search, prove,</hi> and <hi>believe</hi> for thy self. And finally, be faithfull to the witnesse of God in thy conscience, and walk in his fear, so shalt thou find rest, and peace to thy pretious Soul, in life and in death.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204995:3"/>
            <head>Rabshakeh's Outrage REPROVED. OR, A Whip for <hi>William Grigge</hi> of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> Tanner, <hi>To Scourge him,</hi> For his many notorious lies, blasphemies, reproaches, vain boastings, and other such like noysom matter vomited out against the Truth, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>1</label> TRUTH in all Ages hath had the
<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum pessimi tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba est.</hi> Senec. <hi>de Vit. beat.</hi>
               </note> fewest friends for number; and those for quality, not cull'd out from among the <hi>noble,</hi> the <hi>worldly wise,</hi> the <hi>mighty,</hi> the <hi>learned</hi> &amp;c. But (through all ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations) the <hi>base,</hi> the <hi>foolish,</hi> the <hi>weak,</hi> and the <hi>ignoble</hi> hath the Lord chosen, to be pillars of his truth, and to bear his name among the <hi>Gentiles.</hi> Whence it hath constantly come to passe, that they who in the judgment of man's rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, have seemed the most likely persons, to make Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants in God's Kingdom, have stumbled at the <hi>Corner stone,</hi> and so shut themselves out; and having regard to truth's inglorious, and despicable out-side, (making the vote of the multitude the standard of their election) have proved it's fiercest persecutors, and violently exploded it under the notion of <hi>error,</hi> and <hi>blasphemy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:204995:4"/>
            <p>For a proof of which, we need seek no farther than this present age; in which it's become even an honour, in the esteem of many outwardly Religious, to be casting stones at the despised friends of truth: and every envious profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing Jew, that hath learned but so much Scripture, as to be able to cry, <hi>Blasphemy, Blasphemy, Crucifie him, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him,</hi> is by the bloody teachers presently judged meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be canonized among the number of their devoutest Parish-Saints.</p>
            <p>Must not <hi>William Grigge</hi> (think ye) from this time for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, be recorded for a <hi>zealous</hi> man for the cause of God? who having heaped together the <hi>scraps</hi> of <hi>Ralph Farmers Fire-balls,</hi> and the <hi>Chipps</hi> of some of <hi>John Pauls wooden Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> doth therewith make such a blaze in the late defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> strutting and vaunting himself with such Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gisteriall <hi>arrogancy,</hi> ttampling upon one, insulting over another, and condemning all that are contrary to himself, as if he were Commissioned by his Ghostly fathers the Priests, to break all the bonds of truth, and sobernesse, so as that, upon the heads of the <hi>Independents, Anabaptists, Quakers,</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries</hi> (as he calleth them) he might cast all manner of <hi>dirt,</hi> and pronounce upon them an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocable curse.</p>
            <p>For which, and many other of his almost unparallel'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solencies, am I now to reckon with him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>2</label> And first I shall begin with his Epistle to his <hi>Friends,</hi> and <hi>Fellow-Citizens.</hi> In which his principall businesse is, first to cry out against <hi>liberty of conscience,</hi> under the notion of <hi>a wicked toleration;</hi> And secondly, to enveigh against the <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>printing</hi> of those whom he calleth <hi>Gifted bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the first he maketh much ado, whining and complaining in such expressions as these: <hi>There were never sadder times.</hi> And, <hi>is it not sad?</hi> And, <hi>are not these sad times?</hi> And <hi>doth it not call for mourning, and that (if it were possible) with tears of blood?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:204995:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Why <hi>William?</hi> what's the matter? Oh, <hi>this intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>John Knowls,</hi> the Priest thought not liberty of conscience to be an intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when he first went to New <hi>England</hi> to seek it.</note>
               <hi>toleration!</hi> I and my Masters the Priests, and the rest of but Brethren, did vigou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ously prosecute the cause of God, in thrusting the Bishops out or their <hi>Chaires,</hi> with a full dependance to have got into them <hi>our selves,</hi> and did well hope ere this, to have had the necks of all dissenters under our <hi>feet,</hi> and to have made the <hi>little finger</hi> of <hi>PRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYTERY,</hi> sit heavier upon the consciences of all Sectaries than the Bishops <hi>Loynes.</hi> Fain would we have had the blood of some of them ere this, but (ah, these <hi>Souldiers,</hi> these <hi>Souldiers!</hi>) we have been still hindered. We have left no stone unturned, but have with an unwearied industry sought to get into the <hi>Chaire,</hi> working sometimes with our dear <hi>brethren</hi> the <hi>Scots,</hi> sometimes with some discontented swordmen in <hi>England;</hi> and now at last, when we travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with a confident expectation to have obtained <hi>a coercive power</hi> from the late Parliament, we have also brought forth the wind.</p>
            <p>We have esteemed it our priviledge, and our duty, to give rules to all other mens faith, and set bounds (which upon paine of <hi>death</hi> or <hi>banishment</hi> they may not transgresse) to all other mens consciences: But alas! we find (to our great grief) strength of opposition made, and maintained, against such our <hi>desired soveraignty,</hi> by a generation of factious <hi>Independents,</hi> stiffnecked <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and Stubborn <hi>Quakers;</hi> who deny subjection to those <hi>yoaks</hi> which we would impose on them. So that we are even payned at the heart, and do <hi>fret</hi> our selves away (especially my Master <hi>Ralph Farmer,</hi> and my self) with <hi>anguish</hi> of spirit. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we our selves have liberty to our hearts desire, to <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>professe</hi> what we will in matters of Religion; yet that others should enjoy the <hi>same</hi> liberty with us, This, Oh This, grieveth us, and is cause of <hi>deep humiliati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this is <hi>William Grigg's</hi> inward sense (if he durst speak it out) is more then manifest, not onely by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his whole discourse, but also by what he drops in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204995:5"/>expresse words, in the last page of his Pamphlet: where he maketh it his prayer, that those <hi>in power would prove such happy reformers to the Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">☞</note>
               <hi>as to put a restraint upon all soul-infecting persons;</hi> and wisheth, that the <hi>Parliament had made the Nation so happy, as to compell people to Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> &amp;c. That is, in plain English therefore, that they would <hi>inforce</hi> such a subjection to a <hi>lordly</hi> Presbytery, that the whole Nation must see with <hi>their</hi> eyes, walk with <hi>their</hi> feet, and believe what <hi>they</hi> decree for truth; or else sacrifise their <hi>lives,</hi> or at least their <hi>liberties,</hi> to their <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous,</hi> and <hi>unsatiable</hi> appetites.</p>
            <p>And, Reader, remember what I say (especially you that are <hi>William Griggs fellow-Citizens</hi>) if ever you should live to see that <hi>dismal</hi> day come upon England, in which the Reins of its government should be put into the hands of <hi>blood-thirsty</hi> Presbytery, I do verily believe, it would soon become the saddest Theater of <hi>persecution,</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> that ever the Sun did shine on.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>3</label> And now being on this subject, before I passe it over, I shall a little reason with <hi>William Grigge</hi> touching <hi>liberty of conscience,</hi> which he calleth <hi>a wicked toleration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let me ask thee, doest not thou esteem it an equall thing, that thou shouldest have liberty (being under ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans power) to <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>professe</hi> in the things of Religion, what thou in thy <hi>own</hi> conscience art perswaded is the right? If so, is it not then as equal that another should have the <hi>same</hi> liberty from thee, supposing him to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thy power? If thou say, Ay but I do believe the <hi>right,</hi> and he the <hi>wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This hath no weight in it; for, he is as really perswaded in <hi>his</hi> conscience of the truth of what <hi>he</hi> believeth, as <hi>thou</hi> canst be of what <hi>thou</hi> believest; and consequently, by thy own law of equity thou art obliged to give <hi>him</hi> the same liberty, being under thy power, which thou would'st ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from <hi>him,</hi> wer't thou under <hi>his.</hi> For as the
<note n="(c)" place="margin">In his Speech of the 22 Jan. 1654. to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the painted Chamber.</note>
               <hi>PROTECTOR</hi> did rationally ask thy imposing gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>Is it ingenuous to ask liberty, and not to give it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:204995:5"/> 2. Is not every man's soul most precious to <hi>himself?</hi> If so, is it not most reasonable, that he should have liberty to adventure the eternall <hi>well,</hi> or <hi>ill</hi>-being of that precious thing, upon what <hi>he</hi> himself is perswaded to be the <hi>right,</hi> rather then on that which <hi>another</hi> (to whom his soul can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be so dear) concludeth to be so?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Put Case, that a certain number of thy <hi>Fellow-Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens</hi> should come to thee, and say: <hi>William Grigge,</hi> when thou hast occasion of a Physitian, we do require thee to use <hi>this</hi> man, for <hi>we</hi> judge him the most able: And when thou would'st be trim'd, to use <hi>this</hi> Barber, and be trim'd after <hi>this</hi> manner: And when thou needest any garment, to use <hi>this</hi> Taylor, and have thy garment made after <hi>this</hi> fashion: and all this, upon pain of imprisonment, or confiscation of thy estate. Would'st thou not cry out of <hi>this,</hi> as most injurious dealing, and the height of <hi>oppression?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then mind, If thou would'st not have <hi>another</hi> impose upon <hi>thy</hi> judgment, or give rules to <hi>thy</hi> choice, in these <hi>trivial</hi> matters that concern thy <hi>body</hi> that must perish; is it not ten thousand times more <hi>cruelty,</hi> and <hi>oppression,</hi> to impose Laws upon other mens <hi>consciences,</hi> in those <hi>weighty</hi> matters that concern the everlasting being of their immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall <hi>souls?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether, whatsoever is not of <hi>faith,</hi> be <hi>not sin?</hi> and consequently, if all those which thou callest <hi>Anabaptists, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries,</hi> in the Nation (supposing them to be out of the way of truth) should, by thy <hi>Synodical clubb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law,</hi> be compelled in <hi>words</hi> to own the Presbyterian <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, way of worship,</hi> and <hi>discipline,</hi> whilst in their <hi>hearts</hi> they deny them all: whether were they not by such a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, verbal, conformity (their <hi>faith</hi> being contrary) become, even in thy own esteem, <hi>seven fold more the children of the Devil, then they were before?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Thou confessest, in page 30th of thy Pamphet, that thou hast in thee <hi>the seeds of Apostasie.</hi> Suppose then, that that <hi>seed</hi> should so far grow in thee, as that thou shouldest in a short time come to professe that, which <hi>now</hi> thou
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204995:6"/>esteemest <hi>Heresy, Blasphemy,</hi> and <hi>Damnable doctrine:</hi> and those whom thou now revilest under the names of Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, Quakers, &amp;c. should by that time become Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Whether wouldest thou esteem it righteous in them (being back't with <hi>civil power</hi>) to <hi>imprison, fine, scourge,</hi> or <hi>banish</hi> thee, as an Heretick? Or, whether wouldest thou not plead <hi>liberty of conscience;</hi> and rather expect that they should use <hi>love, patience, perswasion,</hi> and by other Gospel weapons rather endeavour to <hi>reclaim</hi> thee, than by the <hi>sword,</hi> and the <hi>clubb,</hi> seek to <hi>destroy</hi> thee? And if so, then how far art thou now removed in thy principles, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice from that <hi>Royall law of love,</hi> which teacheth thee to <hi>do to others, as thou wouldst they should do unto thee?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Lastly, when a certain Instrument called the <hi>Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> was (in the late Infancy of this Common-wealth) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed on the Nation; did'st not thou refuse to take the same? urging this as an Apologie for thy refusal, that it was contrary to the <hi>liberty</hi> of thy conscience? And, could'st thou plead liberty of conscience against a <hi>civil</hi> imposition then,
<note place="margin">☞</note> and hast thou now so much forgotten thy own plea, as that nothing will satisfie thee now, but compulsion, even in things that are of an <hi>inward,</hi> and <hi>spiritual</hi> considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Was Presbytery the onely babe, that was born into the world, sole heir to <hi>liberty</hi> of conscience? and all other professions appointed to be its <hi>vassals,</hi> and <hi>bondmen?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hast thou never read (and in thy Pamphlet thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendest to much reading) in what part of the world that Devilish policy is practised <hi>(viz.)</hi> that the heir to the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire</hi> destroyeth all his <hi>brethren,</hi> lest they should haply live in processe of time, to justle him out of the <hi>Throne?</hi> Hath not <hi>Presbytery</hi> (our pretended elder Brother) been for se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall years past striving to <hi>usurpe</hi> this Hellish power, that when all other professions would be content onely with <hi>life,</hi> and liberty to live, this imperious <hi>bratt</hi> would not suffer them to breathe in the common aire?</p>
            <p>Thou savest in page 48 of thy Pamphlet, that, <hi>some are of opinion, that had the Anabaptists power, their quarter and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204995:6"/>termes might be as bad (if not worse) as what</hi> Nahash <hi>offered the men of</hi> Jabish Gilead <hi>which was,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2.</note>
               <hi>to thrust out all their right eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To which I say, What that people would do, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not determine (though I have not that perswasion of them) but this I am confident of, that, hadst thou and thy cruel generation, but <hi>commission,</hi> as large as your <hi>wills,</hi> it would not be the <hi>eyes</hi> of Anabaptists, and other Sectaries would satisfie you; unlesse you did tear out their <hi>hearts;</hi> and if the Anabaptists might grate upon the <hi>skin,</hi> you would tear the <hi>flesh,</hi> and break the <hi>bones.</hi> What a dismal <hi>slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-house,</hi> and a black <hi>Tophet</hi> of burning, would England soon become, were the sword once gotten into the hands of an <hi>imperious</hi> Presbytery? Should that cloudy day ever come upon the Nation, I am fully perswaded, that the dayes of the <hi>Marian</hi> persecutions, being compared there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, would be as a year of <hi>Jubile,</hi> to a year of hard <hi>servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> and <hi>bondage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall not burden the Reader with prolixity; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore shall close what I have to say touching liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science (which this man of envy calleth <hi>a wicked toleration</hi>) with this; That, whatsoever persecuteth is not of <hi>God,</hi> but of the <hi>Devil:</hi> to whom I know nothing does render a man more like, than to persecute another for conscience sake. So that, let men <hi>professe,</hi> and <hi>pretend,</hi> never so high, and talk of <hi>God, Christ, Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. never so Saint-like; whilst they seek to imbrue their hands in the blood of those, who cannot believe and professe as they do, their faith and profession is no better then that of <hi>Devils.</hi> And, were I constrained to make my election of one, I would choose rather to be found (in the day that the Lord shall come to judge the world) a just-dealing <hi>Indian</hi> in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> then a Zealous professing-persecutor in England.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>4</label> So much of liberty of conscience. The greatest part of his invectives, in the remaining part of his Epistle, are spent upon those he calleth <hi>Gifted brethren.</hi> Against whom he expresseth himself very bitterly angry, <hi>whose pride</hi> (he saith)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204995:7"/>
               <hi>hath led them to that boldnesse in Presse, and Pulpit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> But stay <hi>William,</hi> what art thou? art not thou <hi>a gifted Brother?</hi> would'st thou not take it ill to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise esteemed? and what was it but thy pride, that hath led <hi>thee</hi> to that height of <hi>boldnesse</hi> in the <hi>Presse?</hi> Being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scious to thy self of thy own guilt, thou the better know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est how (as here thou doest) to impeach another of the same crime. He declareth it (in the same Epistle) to be <hi>contrary to his judgment, that men (under the notion of gifted brethren) should so OFT be seen in the Presse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Observe, Reader, <hi>William Grigge</hi> durst not quite block up the <hi>Presse,</hi> against all <hi>gifted brethren;</hi> for then he had secluded himself: and therefore he leaveth a little gap to creep in by, saying, they should not <hi>oft be seen</hi> there. The door of just liberty must stand so far open, as the hand of <hi>Presbytery</hi> pleaseth; but wider then that <hi>Lordly</hi> thing's judgment approveth of, it may not be opened. But <hi>William,</hi> let me ask thee, may not he that hath <hi>a gift</hi> given him of the Lord, <hi>use it?</hi> Was it the part of the slothfull ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to <hi>wrap</hi> his <hi>tallent in a Napkin,</hi> and not improve it, because he had but one? <hi>Is not the manifestation of the</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.7.</note>
               <hi>spirit given to every man to profit withal,</hi> as well others as himself? Nay doth not the spirit of the Lord lay it as a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall <hi>injunction</hi> upon all, that as
<note n="(e)" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note>
               <hi>every one hath received the gift, so</hi> he should <hi>Minister.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But saith <hi>William Grigge,</hi> Nay, <hi>had every gifted Brother grace to his gifts, that doth not commission him to Preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Reader, whom must we believe, <hi>W. Grigge,</hi> or the Scripture? The Scripture saith <hi>this,</hi> he saith <hi>nay.</hi> These are the men that cry out of others, Oh they deny the Scripture; whereas whilest they take the Scriptures to <hi>prate</hi> and <hi>talk</hi> of, to make a covering for their wickednesse, they have the impudence to <hi>contradict</hi> the expresse sayings thereof.</p>
            <p>But put the case that this <hi>Gifted brother</hi> (as thou callest him) should post away to some convention of <hi>persecuting Presbyters,</hi> and (being by them Catechized, and found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204995:7"/>sufficiently <hi>ignorant,</hi> and <hi>impudent,</hi> to make a Parish Priest) should receive from them the <hi>imposition</hi> of their <hi>polluted</hi> hands; would this be an Authentick Commission to impower him to <hi>teach?</hi> By such their imposition they can g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve <hi>nothing,</hi> then he receiveth <hi>nothing:</hi> and conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently what is that <hi>ridiculous</hi> formality, more then an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish imitation, a meer mock-shew, to blind the eyes of the simple?</p>
            <p>Thou say<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st farther in thy Epistle, <hi>That if we would keep to rule, none should take upon him that honourable calling of the Ministry, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> And wilt thou stand to this? Then see, <hi>Aaron</hi> was called to the High Priest-hood by an <hi>immediate call</hi> from the Lord. And what then are all those whom thou callest Ministers in England (by thy own argument) but <hi>intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders?</hi> who are so far from being <hi>called of God as was</hi> Aaron, (viz.) by an <hi>immediate</hi> call; that it is the thing which with one lip they do passionately <hi>disown,</hi> and to which they bid publick <hi>defiance.</hi> So that whilst thou seemest to act the part of an <hi>advocate</hi> for thy <hi>godly, discerning, Orthodox</hi> Divines, thou hast with thy own lipps concluded them to be but a generation of <hi>Intruders;</hi> who (to use thy own words) <hi>do take upon them that honourable calling,</hi> but are <hi>not thereunto called of God, as was</hi> Aaron. I believe the rest of the fraternity will give those <hi>Priests,</hi> that mod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deled and corrected thy Coppy, but small thanks, for letting this plain truth passe the <hi>Presse</hi> without either clip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or correction.</p>
            <p>Thou tellest thy friends, in another place of thy Epistle; that <hi>what thou shalt speak to,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>will not be by way of teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for thou darest not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What? is lying become a <hi>vertue</hi> with thee, <hi>William;</hi> that thou canst so confidently shew thy self <hi>a lyar</hi> in print? Let the honest Reader judge if thou doest not play the <hi>Doctor</hi> (though very bunglingly) and undertake to <hi>teach</hi> in more then <hi>twenty</hi> places of thy Pamphlet; and yet hast thou so much brasse upon thy face, as to tell thy Reader,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204995:8"/>that thou <hi>darest not teach?</hi> Was the consideration of this one reason that moved thee in thy Epistle, to <hi>beg</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Whence had the Priests of <hi>England</hi> this power to grant Pardons, from Heaven, or from Rome?</note>
               <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> of thy <hi>godly, ordained Ministers</hi> (as thou callest them) for <hi>taking this boldnesse in printing, confessing</hi> it to be thy <hi>first fault in that kind, and promising it shall be thy last?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Reader, Is not the Book that followeth like to prove a monstrous piece; for his <hi>boldnesse</hi> in <hi>printing</hi> which, he beggeth <hi>pardon</hi> in the Epistle? Had there been nought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in it, but the savory words of <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>sobernesse,</hi> what need of a <hi>pardon</hi> for <hi>printing</hi> it? But, <hi>William,</hi> either in this confession thy <hi>heart</hi> and <hi>tongue</hi> do go together, or they do not; if, what thou confessest here with thy lipps to be thy <hi>fault,</hi> thou judgest otherwise of in thy <hi>heart,</hi> then thou art a notorious <hi>Hypocrite;</hi> but if thy <hi>heart</hi> speak with thy <hi>mouth</hi> in this thy publick confession, then let all men mind what a <hi>hardned</hi> offender thou art, who did'st yet <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,</hi> and <hi>premeditately</hi> proceed to do that, which before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand thou was convinced to be thy <hi>fault,</hi> and for which thou beggest <hi>pardon.</hi> Twere well, if with a repenting heart thou wert brought to beg <hi>pardon</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, for all the <hi>falshoods, slanders,</hi> and <hi>evil sayings,</hi> with which thy Book doth abound; that so from Him thou mayest receive remission of thy sins, before the hand of <hi>death</hi> cut thee off, and the <hi>grave</hi> shut her mouth upon thee, where there will be <hi>no place</hi> left for <hi>Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>5</label> I had now done with <hi>W. Grigge</hi>'s Epistle, but that in the last leaf thereof he will needs shew us what an able <hi>Critick</hi> he is about words. The man hath (as they that live neer him do well know) an imbred popular <hi>Ambition</hi> to appear some body among men: although he hath wholly mist of his aime, in the judgment of all that are <hi>wise,</hi> and <hi>sober,</hi> not only in this his <hi>strife about words</hi> (which he himself as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serteth to be one <hi>evill sign of Seducers</hi>) but in the whole matter of his <hi>rayling, abusive</hi> Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>He falleth outragiously foul upon the people called Quakers, for <hi>tying themselves to the words, YEA,</hi> and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204995:8"/>
               <hi>NAY.</hi> And thereupon offereth to consideration, the sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the two
<note n="(h)" place="margin">1 King. 3.20, 21.</note>
               <hi>Mothers,</hi> that strove before <hi>Solomon</hi> about the <hi>living child.</hi> In which he observeth, that the <hi>preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mother</hi> used the word <hi>NAY,</hi> and the <hi>true mother</hi> the word, <hi>NO.</hi> And then for the other word, he saith that
<note n="(i)" place="margin">Mat. 17.25.</note>
               <hi>Peter</hi> answereth <hi>YES,</hi> but
<note n="(k)" place="margin">Act. 5.8.</note>
               <hi>Saphira (who was privy to her Husbands Hypocrisie)</hi> used the word, <hi>YEA.</hi> And upon this, the blind Zealot goeth on <hi>insulting,</hi> as if he had gotten the day, and knock't all in the head, telling his friends in this domineering Language, <hi>So then you have here a fit pair of hppocrites,</hi> (meaning the pretended Mother and <hi>Saphira</hi>) <hi>to make Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. It's past all dispute, that the man doth not a little <hi>glory</hi> in himself, that he hath offered such <hi>a curious</hi> peece of learning as this to the view of the world. Nor may we think, but that his <hi>fellow-disciples</hi> in <hi>Bristol</hi> (especially the <hi>underlings</hi> that are of the lower form) do much <hi>admire</hi> him, for <hi>a profound,</hi> and <hi>mighty man</hi> in the Scriptures, who could bring forth such <hi>choise</hi> observations as these. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, upon a serious scrutiny, we shall find, that they are but the <hi>mishappen bratts,</hi> of his own <hi>ignorance</hi> and <hi>impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the two mothers that pleaded before <hi>Solomon,</hi> about the <hi>living child,</hi> did answer by
<note n="(l)" place="margin">
                  <p>King. 3.22. The preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mother said.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> non. And the true mother said.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </note>
               <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>same</hi> word in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> (being the Language in which they spake) Although it pleased the Translator to render it from the mouth of the one, <hi>NO,</hi> and from the mouth of the other, <hi>NAY.</hi> So likewise did <hi>Peter,</hi> and
<note n="(m)" place="margin">
                  <p>Mar. 17.25.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peter</hi> saith. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </note>
               <hi>Saphira,</hi> answer by <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>same</hi> word in the
<note n="(n)" place="margin">
                  <p>And Act. 5.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Saphira</hi> saith. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
               </note>
               <hi>Greek</hi> (being the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage in which they spake) although, as spoken by <hi>Peter,</hi> it be translated, <hi>YES;</hi> and as spoken by <hi>Saphira,</hi> it be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>slated, <hi>YEA.</hi> And both of them spake that <hi>same</hi> word, that
<note n="(o)" place="margin">Mat. 5.38. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Christ used, when he Commanded his hearers to let their <hi>Communication be YEA, YEA:</hi> So that the <hi>pretended</hi> mother and the <hi>true</hi> mother, and <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> speaking by <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>same</hi> word (each in their Language) though <hi>differently</hi> rendred in the English; look
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204995:9"/>what force thy senselesse argument hath, to prove the one to be a Hypocrite for <hi>so</hi> speaking, the same it hath to prove the other to be so also. And consequently thou wilt blasphemously conclude, the <hi>true</hi> mother, <hi>Peter,</hi> and the <hi>holy men of God</hi> in Scriptures, that used the <hi>same</hi> Language, nay Jesus Christ himself (in <hi>whose mouth was never guile found</hi>) under the condemnation of <hi>Hypocrites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>William,</hi> see what all thy noise, and fluttering, about the words <hi>YEA,</hi> and <hi>NAY</hi> is come to; by which thou hast declared thy self thus <hi>impudently ignorant</hi> to all the world.</p>
            <p>How much better had it become thee to abide in thy honest vocation, and have minded the well handling of thy <hi>Hydes,</hi> rather then so insultingly engage in a disputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about <hi>words,</hi> in managing which thou hast so <hi>ignorant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> handled the Scriptures. Had thy <hi>masters</hi> (those Priests that dress'd and deck't thy <hi>Babe</hi> before it passed the Presse to the worlds view) delt ingenuously by thee, they must needs have prevented thee, from thus shamefully splitting thy great name of <hi>a learned man</hi> in the Scriptures, upon a rock so visible, that he that hath but <hi>half</hi> an eye, might at a distance discern, and avoyd it. Unlesse they did presume that thy Book should never come to the view, or perusall, of any, but such as are as <hi>blinde</hi> as thy self, who durst pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumptuously publish any thing for truth, which hath passed the Priests approbation.</p>
            <p>I have now done with <hi>William Grigg</hi>'s Epistle; and shall proceed to a brief examination of his Book; his <hi>boldnesse in printing, which</hi> he confesseth (in his Epistle) to be his <hi>fault,</hi> and accordingly <hi>beggs pardon</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>A. Greater wickednesse then which who can suppose? what? confesse a thing to be thy <hi>fault,</hi> and <hi>begg pardon</hi> for it, and yet knowingly proceed to act it? Is this that by which thou tell'st thy Reader in the same Epistle, thou wast <hi>perswaded by some godly Christians, that God would have glory,</hi> and by which thou speakest of <hi>Christ and his Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces being exalting?</hi> Monstrous blasphemy! Can that which
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204995:9"/>is thy <hi>fault,</hi> and for which thou <hi>beggest pardon,</hi> bring <hi>glory</hi> to God, or exalt Christ? What God doest thou serve other then <hi>the God of this World (who hath blinded thine eyes)</hi> whom thou supposest capable of receiving <hi>glory</hi> from that, which thou thy self confessest to be thy <hi>fault,</hi> and for which thou <hi>beggest pardon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>7</label>
               <hi>William Grigge</hi> beginneth his Pamphlet with a frivolous, impertinent story of a Book <hi>lent him by Dennis Hollister a Quaker,</hi> and his returning it (after reading) to him again <hi>being in his Shopp, walking with</hi> Thomas Goulding, <hi>a Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> And then relateth what <hi>Dennis Hollister</hi> told him, and what he <hi>answered,</hi> &amp;c. and so he <hi>left them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. And what of all this? what entertainment is here for the thoughts of an <hi>ingenuous</hi> Reader? Sure, the man did conclude that every one to whose view his Pamphlet should come, had as much spare time to <hi>read,</hi> as he had to <hi>print</hi> such idle Stories as these. His practice in this is very suitable to that of his Masters the Priests in their Pulpits, many of whom bring forth any manner of <hi>impertinencies,</hi> to fill up the hour; and being obliged to speak for such a space of time, do stuffe their discourses with any <hi>wood, hay,</hi> and <hi>stubble,</hi> to answer the expectations of their deluded hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>8</label> In page the 3d he beginneth his Narrative of <hi>James Nay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor,</hi> his riding into <hi>Bristoll,</hi> his <hi>examinations, sufferings,</hi> &amp;c. to follow him in all which, is neither my businesse, nor my purpose; enough hath been already said thereof by <hi>other</hi> pens. My task shall be briefly to detect him in all that <hi>pride, malice, falshood,</hi> and <hi>hypocrisy,</hi> which he hath mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested throughout his Pamphlet.</p>
            <p>And first in the same Narrative, I cannot but take notice how his hand of <hi>rage</hi> doth catch at every shadow of a dart, to wound (if possible) the sides of those, whose blood would be as welcome a present to <hi>him,</hi> as was the head of <hi>John</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.11.</note>
               <hi>Baptist</hi> to blood-thirsting <hi>Herodias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He saith James Naylor <hi>rode to the</hi> White Hart <hi>in</hi> Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street, <hi>being the house of</hi> Dennis Hollister, <hi>and</hi> Henry Roe, <hi>both Eminent Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:204995:10"/>
            <p> A. Here he hath manifested more <hi>wickednesse,</hi> then <hi>wit;</hi> and more <hi>envy,</hi> then <hi>truth.</hi> A mind he hath to cast a stone or two at <hi>Dennis Hollister,</hi> and <hi>Henry Roe</hi> in passing; and if he can find none, he will adventure to make a stone. What if the <hi>White-hart</hi> were their house? then that must entitle them to the then-proceedings of <hi>James Naylor?</hi> they must be one with him in what he then did, for he <hi>rode</hi> to their house. Put the case, <hi>William,</hi> that thou had'st a house in <hi>Bristoll</hi> possessed by one that gave entertainment to <hi>Drunkards, Swearers, Whore-masters,</hi> and all sorts of <hi>prophane</hi> persons: would'st thou esteem it good Logick, that <hi>Den. Hollister,</hi> and <hi>Hen. Roe</hi> should argue thus of thee, <hi>William Grigge</hi> is <hi>one</hi> with <hi>Drunkards, Swearers, Whore-masters,</hi> &amp;c. for that persons so qualified have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times been found in the house of <hi>Will. Grigge.</hi> What mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure thou metest unto others, I hope thou canst not judge unequal for thee to receive.</p>
            <p>But what if the <hi>White-hart</hi> be not the house of <hi>D. H.</hi> and <hi>H. R?</hi> Is not <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> then found to be a most <hi>audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> Lyar? And whether the house be theirs or not, let the honest Reader judge, by what followeth.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Upon the death of one <hi>Edmond Poply,</hi> the <hi>White-hart</hi> fell to his four Sisters, <hi>Anne Yeamans, Elizabeth French, Bridget Hollister,</hi> and <hi>Judeth Roe,</hi> of which house there was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ease granted to one <hi>John Pierce,</hi> for one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years, to commence from the year sixteen hundred fourty nine; which <hi>Pierce</hi> is since dead, and the house enjoyed by one <hi>Nicholas Fox,</hi> who payeth the rent reser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the said Lease, to the said four Sisters, of which Rent <hi>D. H.</hi> and <hi>H. R.</hi> (in right of their wifes) do receive their parts.</q>
            </p>
            <p>By which, Reader, thou mayest see how disingenuously malicious this man is, who (that he might entitle these two persons to that which he trusted might render them odious) had the <hi>impudence</hi> to entitle them to a house, with which they had no more to do then before thou hast heard.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:204995:10"/>
            <p> He proceedeth on to declare in the same Narrative, That <hi>the Magistrates sent for</hi> James Naylor, <hi>the Quaker's Jesus, and his Disciples, seven in number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What a mist doth <hi>rage</hi> draw over the eyes of the envious? who (striving with their <hi>Maker</hi>) do so far lose the common understanding of men, that what through <hi>envy</hi> they seek to <hi>establish,</hi> themselves do <hi>overthrow,</hi> by their own <hi>contradictions.</hi> See how <hi>witty W. G.</hi> is in his arguing. <hi>James Naylor</hi> is the <hi>Quaker's Jesus.</hi> How is that proved?
<note place="margin">☜</note> By the multitude of his disciples, they were <hi>seven in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi> Doest thou not know that, there are many more then seven <hi>hundred</hi> of the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> in, and about the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> among whom thou canst not name a person that made one in that number of seven? And were there not many <hi>hundreds</hi> of the same people, dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persed here, and there, through out this Nation, who were not so much as <hi>privy</hi> to the then-deportment, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions of <hi>J. N.</hi> and his <hi>seven disciples?</hi> and yet to all these must he needs be a <hi>Jesus?</hi> Hath thy malice against the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, extinguisht the very glimmerings of common rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in thee, that thou doest thus shamefully cast up such puddle of <hi>nonsense,</hi> and <hi>contradictions</hi> as this?</p>
            <p>If thou hast yet any thing left in thee to judge withall, betwixt right and wrong, reflect but upon thy argument with which the <hi>envious one</hi> hath furnished thee, and be ashamed of thy <hi>folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>James Naylor</hi> came into <hi>Bristoll</hi> with his disciples be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>seven</hi> in number, and there be in, and about, the same City more then <hi>seven hundred</hi> people called Quakers, of whom not <hi>one</hi> was of that number of <hi>se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and by whom those <hi>seven</hi> were publickly <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> Then <hi>J. N.</hi> is the <hi>Quakers Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>J. N.</hi> came into <hi>Bristoll</hi> with <hi>seven</hi> disciples, and there are more then <hi>seven hundred</hi> of the people called Quakers, in, and about the same City, of whom not <hi>one</hi> was of that number of <hi>seven,</hi> and by whom those seven were publikely <hi>disowned,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:204995:11"/>
            <p> Therefore <hi>J. N.</hi> is the <hi>Quakers Jesus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He that can find <hi>truth</hi> among this heap of <hi>contradictions,</hi> let him. And to thee <hi>W. G.</hi> I say, If madenesse against those that fear the Lord hath not quite blinded thy eyes, if thou hast not contracted a coveting of <hi>Adamant</hi> upon thy heart, and of <hi>brasse</hi> upon thy forehead, blush and be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, blasphemously to call <hi>a man</hi> that must dye, that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple's Jesus, who own no other for their Saviour, but him <hi>that was with the Father in the</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Joh. 1.2, 3. Joh. 8.56.</note>
               <hi>beginning, by whom all things were made; whose day</hi> Abraham <hi>saw, and rejoyced:</hi> whom <hi>Saul</hi> (whilst in thy nature) persecuted; and of whom thou also art at this day (though in <hi>words</hi> a professor, yet in <hi>deed</hi>) an outragious persecutor.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>9</label> In page the 12th, <hi>W. G.</hi> will needs give his Reader a tast of his <hi>Oratory,</hi> by printing that <hi>wooden</hi> speech he made before the Committee appointed to examine <hi>J. N.</hi> in the Painted Chamber. His abilities to speak (Oracle-like) in which he doth not a little glory, had been concealed, had not this quaint peece of <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>eloquence,</hi> been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished to the worlds view.</p>
            <p>He saith that <hi>Mr.</hi> Phillip Dorney, <hi>and (upon the request of the Magistrates) another with him, to evidence what here they</hi> (viz. <hi>J. N.</hi> and his seven disciples) <hi>said, went for</hi> London &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Why had'st thou not spoke out plainly, and said, I, <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> of <hi>Bristoll, Tanner,</hi> swelling ready to burst with <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>envy,</hi> at the <hi>small</hi> request of the Magistrates (begotten by my own forwardnesse) with hopes to have <hi>Naylor's blood,</hi> and to make my self <hi>famous,</hi> among my tender-hearted brethren of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> did ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to <hi>London</hi> to <hi>shew</hi> my self, and spend some to the <hi>Citie's</hi> money (to little purpose) and so return. And (without reflection upon the Magistrates of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stoll</hi> their wisdom) let me say it, It was not their Master-piece, in sending such <hi>a busie, pragmatical</hi> person as thou art to <hi>London,</hi> there to make <hi>a speech</hi> (to a Committee of Parliament) which had in it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>head,</hi> nor <hi>taile,</hi> nor good <hi>sense,</hi> nor <hi>reason;</hi> but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204995:11"/>(for the greatest part) composed of, <hi>fawning, falshood,</hi> and pittifull lame complements, crying <hi>Sir, Gentlemen,</hi> and <hi>your Honours,</hi> but speaking nothing of weight or impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, relating to the matter then in debate.</p>
            <p>Reader, thou must know that this envious person is a great <hi>Speech-maker</hi> in the Common Council of <hi>Bristoll;</hi> and if he had so high an esteem of <hi>this</hi> which he made in the painted Chamber, as to judge it <hi>polite,</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> enough to merit the publick view, thou mayest thence easily judge, what <hi>sad</hi> oratory do serve the turn within the walls of that Council. But who can tell what the reason should be, that <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> whilst he was making his speech was (by his own confession) <hi>three</hi> times bid to <hi>speak on?</hi> Sure the man was about to make some teadious preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (for he dearly loves to hear himself speak) <hi>grievous</hi> to be borne by any ingenuous ears, which made the hearers very willing to be eased of their burden.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William Grigge</hi> saith that one of the witnesses (meaning himself) was <hi>called upon by the Committee, to manifest the manner of</hi> J. N. <hi>his coming into</hi> Bristoll; but when it came to, confesseth (a little after in the same page) and telleth the Committee,
<note place="margin">☜</note> that he was <hi>not an eye-witnesse to his coming in.</hi> What then? If he were no <hi>eye-witnesse</hi> to that which he was called to testifie, what went he to <hi>London</hi> for? why, instead of giving testimony to what he <hi>himself</hi> saw, he tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Committee, that the <hi>testimony which the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strates</hi> (viz. of Bristoll) <hi>have sent your Honours, was affirmed by two Gentlemen, that were members of the Common Council of</hi> Bristoll, <hi>who were eye-witnesses.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> A rare witnesse-bearer! who hasteth to <hi>London,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending great <hi>weight</hi> in what he could testifie, touching the matter then in agitation, and beginning his speech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Committee of Parliament</hi> with some <hi>Puffe-past</hi> Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, telleth them, that <hi>upon the request of the Magistrates of</hi> Bristoll <hi>he did there appear,</hi> as if some great matter would follow; and then offereth this as the weight of his <hi>testimony,</hi> viz. that <hi>what the Magistrates had sent to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:204995:12"/>was true, for two members of the Common Council were eye-witnesses thereof.</hi> As if the Mayor, and Aldermen, had not had so much <hi>credit</hi> above as to be believed in their <hi>testimony,</hi> unlesse <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> had gone up to <hi>London</hi> to tell the Committee, that it was <hi>true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>1</label> I would ask <hi>Will. Grigge,</hi> whether he did not refuse to go to <hi>London,</hi> (at least in pretence) untill he had <hi>five</hi> pound paid him in <hi>hand</hi> towards his expences on his journey? What more he received at his return, himself best knoweth.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>2</label> Whether the <hi>testimony</hi> he gave, and the <hi>oration</hi> he made before the <hi>Committee,</hi> were worth the <hi>hundreth</hi> part of the money?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>3</label> Whether the <hi>cause of God</hi> (for so he called it before the Committee) which he was then upon, had been by him at all persecuted, unlesse the <hi>wheele</hi> that drove it on, had been first <hi>oyled</hi> with a competent summe of <hi>silver?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>4</label> Whether the Magistrates of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> might not have been able to give a better account of their <hi>Steward-ship,</hi> both to God and Man, had they bestowed that <hi>five</hi> pound upon five <hi>distressed</hi> families (with which <hi>Bristoll</hi> doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound) rather then spend it upon a person, that should ride <hi>a hundred</hi> miles to tell a Committee of Parliament (as the up-shott of his testimony) that what the <hi>Magistrates had sent up to them, was affirmed by two members of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council of</hi> Bristoll?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Qu. </seg>5</label> Whether it be not a demonstration of a <hi>proud, haughty, vain-glorious</hi> spirit dwelling in this man, to print a speech of his own making before a <hi>Committee of Parliament,</hi> which could have no other end in it, but to let the world see what an able <hi>speaker</hi> he is?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>10</label> From page the 14 of his Pamphlet, to page 24th, we have a relation of the manner of <hi>J. N.</hi> his being <hi>sentenced,</hi> and the same inflicted upon him, in <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Bristoll,</hi> &amp;c. Throughout all which he doth manifest such a spirit of <hi>blood,</hi> and <hi>envy</hi> raging in his breast, that he doth seem to gnash his teeth, and repine, snarsing at one, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204995:12"/>against another, where-ever he saw the least <hi>mercy</hi> appearing, to mitigate the <hi>mercilesse</hi> Stroaks of <hi>cruelty.</hi> And particularly in his <hi>rage,</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> he cannot contain himself from Stigmatizing <hi>Col. Scroope</hi> (sometimes Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Bristoll</hi>) with a brand of reproach <hi>(as he hoped)</hi> for that he was the first, that subscribed the petition to the Parliament, for the remitting of part of <hi>J. N.</hi> his <hi>punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Touching which I have this to say; that the name and the memory of <hi>Col. Scroope</hi> (as to <hi>that</hi> act of his) shall in all ages to come, have <hi>a good</hi> savour in the Nostrills of all that are <hi>sober,</hi> and that do witnesse the <hi>Lamb of God</hi> for their head, and guide; when the name, and the memory, of such <hi>blood-thirsty</hi> persecutors, and <hi>ravenous</hi> destroyers as thou art, shall <hi>rot,</hi> and <hi>stink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In page 21 he doth with anguish of spirit bewaile the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> that it hath not deeplier engaged in <hi>cruelty</hi> and oppression upon the innocent, in <hi>crushing the shell</hi> (as he expresseth it,) <hi>but rather nourishing the brood of this Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine generation of Quakers,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It's little to be doubted, but that if thou, and thy Master <hi>Ralph,</hi> could have had your wills, we should soon have seen the same work made with the <hi>innocent</hi> in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> as
<note n="(r)" place="margin">2 King. 21.16.</note>
               <hi>Manasseh</hi> made with them in <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> And though the hand of the Lord hath so limited your <hi>rage</hi> that that hath been prevented; yet, let me tell thee, that thou needest not wish <hi>more</hi> to rest upon the Citie's score then al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready doth. For, a large account have they to give, to him that is <hi>righteous in judgment,</hi> for the <hi>innocent blood</hi> that hath been shed, and for all the <hi>cruelty,</hi> and <hi>oppression</hi> that hath been exerciled, upon the <hi>persons,</hi> and the <hi>estates</hi> of those▪ that have no helper, but him that is <hi>higher then the highest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the same page he hath this expression <hi>(viz.) These wretched Quakers that would scarce seem to own</hi> Naylor, <hi>at his coming in the</hi> 24th <hi>of</hi> October, <hi>yet now</hi> (viz.) when he was going to <hi>London many accompany him, and use these expressions,</hi> (viz.) <hi>Behold the Lamb of God: This is the corner stone which the Builders refused,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:204995:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I shall passe by the non-sense that is in that sentence, lest I should seem to quarrell at <hi>words;</hi> and minde the thing intended. His purpose is (if possible) to render the <hi>Quakers</hi> in <hi>Bristoll</hi> one with <hi>J. N.</hi> his <hi>seven disciples,</hi> and therefore saith in an indefinite expression. <hi>These wretched Quakers which would scarce own him when he came in</hi> (there he cleareth them) <hi>yet now many accompany him,</hi> &amp;c. Who were those <hi>many?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dolus in uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versalibus.</note> why hadst thou not named them? A Lyar doth find the best covering, by resting in <hi>Generalls.</hi> Certain expressions thou quotest that were used by particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar persons touching <hi>J. N.</hi> (which we must believe because thou hast printed them) what then? why, therefore these <hi>wretched Quakers (though they would not own him at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in, yet now)</hi> are all <hi>one</hi> with his <hi>seven disciples.</hi> Is this good Logick, <hi>William?</hi> untill thou doest quote those <hi>wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Quakers</hi> (as thou callest them) that did <hi>not own him at his coming in,</hi> and yet afterwards used these <hi>expressions</hi> touching him: (which upon dilligent inquiry I am well assured that thou canst never do) thou must stand upon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord for a malicious <hi>Lyar,</hi> and a <hi>false accuser.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>11</label> In page the 24th he beginneth (by a strange diversion) to make a Sermon, with which he filleth no less then <hi>ten</hi> Pages of his <hi>Pamphlet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He had before given his Reader (by printing his speech made in the <hi>Painted Chamber</hi>) a tast of his abilities to play the <hi>State-Oratour:</hi> and now he must needs shew himself also how able he is to <hi>preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having manifested the <hi>blacknesse,</hi> and <hi>cruelty</hi> of his spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in many fore-going particulars, now the subtill-serpent that lodgeth in him, endeavoureth to creep under <hi>a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> made up of a few good words; to beget a belief (if pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible) in the hearts of the Simple, that he is (notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) a <hi>godly</hi> person. The Scribes and Pharisees were in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance very <hi>devout</hi> persons, notable <hi>expounders</hi> of the Scriptures, <hi>Doctors</hi> to the people, <hi>Zealous</hi> for their <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Passover,</hi> &amp;c. and yet <hi>murderers</hi> of the Son of God: Look upon their <hi>outside,</hi> and nothing could you perceive
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204995:13"/>but <hi>zeal,</hi> and <hi>devotion,</hi> and under that very covering did they stand, when they with hearts full of blood, did destroy the <hi>innocent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's not profession, but fruits, <hi>William,</hi> that will bear the tryall when he that is <hi>Righteous</hi> shall come to judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Thou</hi> talk of Christ, and yet <hi>a persecutor?</hi> Is he <hi>thy</hi> Jesus, and thou thirst after the <hi>blood</hi> of his <hi>Lambs? thy</hi> Saviour, and yet <hi>thou</hi> seek to <hi>destroy</hi> those whom he came to <hi>save?</hi> thy mediator, and yet <hi>thou</hi> an advocate against him in his poor <hi>Saints?</hi> Do not deceive thy self; for by thy fruits art thou manifest to the least of the <hi>Children of light,</hi> to be <hi>a stranger</hi> and an <hi>enemy</hi> to the true Christ, wherever he is manifested in <hi>power.</hi> The <hi>members</hi> do partake in their measure, of the <hi>same</hi> spirit with the <hi>head,</hi> Then see what spirit thou art of. The <hi>true</hi> Jesus was a <hi>Lamb,</hi> but in thee is plainly seen the destroying spirit of the <hi>Wolfe.</hi> He was <hi>meek, and lowly,</hi> thou art found conversing in <hi>rage,</hi> and <hi>fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse.</hi> He was <hi>persecuted,</hi> thou art a persecutor; so that (profession excepted) by thy fruits it is manifest, that thou art no more a friend or disciple, to the <hi>meek, holy, innocent, suffering, persecuted</hi> Iesus, then the <hi>Iews</hi> that crucified him at <hi>Ierusalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot omitt the observation of two things, in this <hi>tedious</hi> Sermon that <hi>William Grigge</hi> maketh to his Reader.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The first is, how he seedeth himself with the strange conceptions of his own imaginations: Particularly, spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the <hi>sufferings</hi> of Christ (under the hands of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decessors, the <hi>professing</hi> Iews) he fancieth to himself <hi>twelve bleedings</hi> of Christ; and the Scripture must be his proof: and where that is <hi>silent,</hi> there he <hi>supposeth it</hi> to be so and so: This is the strange liberty these men take to themselves, in pretending to speak according to the Scripture, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead thereof father upon it their <hi>supposed</hi> conclusions, brought forth from the womb of their own vain minds.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The second thing observable, is, how thick he shooteth his darts (yet under a fair pretext) at <hi>the Souldiers,</hi> throughout that whole discourse; And, having thrown as
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204995:14"/>many <hi>stones</hi> at them as well he could, and (as much as in him lay) <hi>wounded</hi> their reputations, he cometh towards the close, to give a plaister to heal them, by telling his Reader, that he do <hi>own Warre as an ordinance of God, when rightly stated</hi> (i. e.) when it is <hi>so stated,</hi> that it may advance the interest he would have <hi>uppermost,</hi> which might <hi>ckeck,</hi> and give rules, and laws, to <hi>all</hi> other interests, which may be in their principles, and practises, of narrower or larger dimensions then it self.</p>
            <p>I have this onely more to say to <hi>William Grigg's</hi> confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Sermon, <hi>(viz.)</hi> That they that built the Sepulchers, of <hi>those</hi> Prophets whom their Fathers <hi>slew,</hi> did crucify the Son of God, of whom the same Prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ets foretold; and did put to death his precious Saints, supposing they had therein done acceptable <hi>service</hi> to his Father. Suitable to which is <hi>W. G's</hi> practise at this day, to talk of <hi>Christ, his</hi> Jesus, <hi>his</hi> Saviour, &amp;c, expressing abundance of seeming <hi>zeal</hi> for his <hi>name,</hi> and yet furiously persecute those his poor <hi>Lambs,</hi> in whom his <hi>life</hi> is manifested in <hi>power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>12</label>
               <hi>William Grigge</hi> having ended his Sermon, beginneth in page the (37) to fall to his proper work of <hi>raging,</hi> and <hi>ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> against the men of his indignation. And particularly he salleth most furiously foul, upon the people called <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> endeavouring to make them to be the <hi>rise,</hi> and <hi>spring</hi> of all that which he calleth <hi>error,</hi> and <hi>blasphemy,</hi> &amp;c. Touching which it's not my purpose to say much, but shall leave that people to vindicate themselves, and wash off that dirt which he most reproachfully hath cast upon them.</p>
            <p>Onely as they stand witnesses against that great <hi>Idol</hi> of <hi>Infant baptisme</hi> (which thou falsly callest an <hi>ordinance of Jesus Chaist</hi>) I cannot but freely give in my testimony with them, and declare; that of all the <hi>groundlesse</hi> practises, found among the <hi>Priests</hi> of England at this day, I do not at present minde that there is any <hi>one,</hi> that hath lesse shadow of ground in the <hi>Scripture</hi> than that of sprinkling Infants. To which testimony I am ready (if thereunto called) to set
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204995:14"/>my seal with my blood: Nor is it a thing difficult from the Scriptures of truth to make it evident, both to the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstandings</hi> and <hi>consciences</hi> of those that are <hi>sober-minded,</hi> and live in Gods fear, That Infant-baptisme was never instituted by Jesus Christ, nor was ever practised as any <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of his, by his Apostles, and holy men after him, of which the Scriptures do make mention.</p>
            <p>In page (41) <hi>W. G.</hi> saith that <hi>Constant Jesup</hi> (sometimes a publick teacher in <hi>Bristoll) was put by his ministery, as to</hi> Bristoll, <hi>to the grief of all that feared the Lord in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What <hi>William?</hi> nor <hi>man</hi> nor <hi>woman,</hi> nor <hi>young</hi> nor <hi>old,</hi> that <hi>feared</hi> God in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> but those that grieved at his being <hi>put by?</hi> what proud Pharisee in the world could have passed a more peremptory sentence then this? What doest thou think of thy Master <hi>Ralph Farmer,</hi> doest not thou in thy Pamphlet call him (more then once) <hi>a godly Minister,</hi> and yet here doest exclude him from the number of those that <hi>fear the Lord?</hi> for if he did shed any <hi>tears</hi> for <hi>C. J.</hi> his being <hi>put by,</hi> they were very
<note n="(s)" place="margin">Crocodili Lachrymae.</note>
               <hi>fained</hi> ones: for sure I am, he was a zealous instigator, and promotor of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movall. What doest thou think of <hi>Mathew Hazard</hi> and <hi>Nathanel Jngelo,</hi> for they were not <hi>grieved</hi> at his being <hi>put by,</hi> if mens hearts may be know by what their lips do utter; and in that business I am confident their <hi>hearts</hi> gave not the lye to their <hi>tongues.</hi> And lastly, what doest thou think of many <hi>scores</hi> both of men, and women, in the City of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> who were not at all grieved at his removall (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse it be upon this consideration that <hi>a worse</hi> is gotten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his place) Was there never a one among all these, that did fear the Lord? You Citizens of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> who were not <hi>grieved</hi> at <hi>Constant Jesup</hi> his being <hi>put by,</hi> look to your selves; for, either <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> is a most malicious false<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accuser, or else your case is <hi>sad.</hi> If the impeachment that he hath exhibited to the world against you stand, you must expect your portion among such as <hi>fear</hi> not the Lord. </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>13</label> Having from page the (37) to page (48) spent much of his <hi>venome,</hi> more particularly against the people called
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204995:15"/>
               <hi>Anabaptists, raging</hi> and raving, and foming out his <hi>envy,</hi> and <hi>ranchor</hi> against them, in a most abusive, and almost unparalell'd manner (manifesting the same spirit against those he calleth <hi>Sectaries,</hi> that <hi>Saul</hi> did against the Saints, when he confesseth before King <hi>Agrippa</hi> and <hi>Festus,</hi> that he was <hi>exceeding</hi>
               <note n="(t)" place="margin">Act. 26.11. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>mad</hi> against them) He cometh in page (49) to cast what <hi>dirt</hi> he can possibly lay hold of, upon the people called <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Before I do particularly examine which, I shall mind the Reader of three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In page the (49) in the close of what he hath to say of the people called <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> he saith, he doth nor <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake disputation, but desireth lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Having with much bitternesse <hi>reviled,</hi> and <hi>trampled</hi> upon their <hi>persons,</hi> and with arguments endeavoured to overthrow their <hi>principles</hi> (and so at once spent both his malice and his logick) now he cometh in a pittifull <hi>faw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> way, to begg the question in hand, and tell his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that he doth not <hi>undertake disputation, but desireth la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And so in page (54) he telleth his <hi>brethren</hi> (i. e. in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution and cruelty) that he doth <hi>not intend con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tation of error</hi> (for he hath <hi>neither time nor ability so to do) but lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Is not here rare justice? that a person who confess<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth he is not <hi>able</hi> to confute <hi>error,</hi> should notwithstanding with such considence, and indignation, pronounce per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons to be <hi>erronious,</hi> and cry to the Magistrate to <hi>execute</hi> them as such, before ever he hath undertaken by the truth to confute them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. It's to be noted, how in juriously unjust this man is, in his proceeding against the men of his anger; in that he taketh the words or actions of <hi>a particular</hi> person, and cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them as a reproach upon the <hi>whole</hi> company called by the same name. Such a one called an <hi>Anabaptist</hi> said so, and did so (and it may be both false) What then? then cry to the Magistrates, Look what a filthy generation these
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204995:15"/>
               <hi>Anabaptists</hi> are, a people not to be tolerated in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; Such a man who is called <hi>a Quaker</hi> said <hi>so,</hi> or did <hi>so,</hi> What then? therefore these <hi>Quakers</hi> are a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked generation, a company of <hi>Blasphemers,</hi> not worthy to live, and breathe in the Common aire. Is this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous judgment, and just measure, <hi>William?</hi> Wilt thou vouch for all the <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>actions</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the people in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland that are called <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and those that do follow the <hi>Priests?</hi> would'st thou este<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m it equal measure meted to thee, if any man should come to thee and say, <hi>Will. Grigge,</hi> thou art a Presbyter, and one that followeth the Priests, therefore thou art <hi>a drunkard, a swearer,</hi> an <hi>unclean</hi> person, <hi>a cheater,</hi> &amp;c. for that such a one, and such a one, that are so called, and do follow the Priests, are so and so? would not this be in thy eyes (as indeed it is) a most <hi>unjust</hi> way of proceeding?</p>
            <p>Or put the case, that the people called <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and <hi>Quakers,</hi> and others whom thou callest <hi>Sectaries,</hi> should apply themselves to the chief Magistrate, and Powers of this Nation, and there exhibit an impeachment against the people called <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and say, Oh these Presbyters that follow the Priests, are a vile, and wicked generation of men; drunkards, for <hi>such</hi> a one, and <hi>such</hi> a one were drunk at such and such times; they are <hi>swearers,</hi> for such a man is called a Presbyter, and followeth the Priests, and he is a common swearer; they are murderers, for that such a one so called was executed at such an Assizes for such a murder; they are unclean persons, for such a one so called, was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken so and so; they are Thieves, Cheaters, &amp;c. for that such persons so called, were at such a time convicted of such crimes: therefore we do declare, that these Presbyters are not to be tolerated, but ought to be punished by <hi>death, bonds,</hi> or <hi>banishment;</hi> would not all sober men cry out shame of such an unequal way of proceeding? would it not savour more of <hi>malice,</hi> then true <hi>zeal?</hi> would'st not thou, and the rest that are called Presbyters, presently answer for your selves, Why? shall the spots of a few <hi>particular</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204995:16"/>and those also whom we own not, be made matter of crime to <hi>thousands</hi> of us that are guiltlesse.</p>
            <p>Then let all that are sober, minde, how contrary to truth, and all honesty, thou proceedest against those, whose blood thou doest thirst after, under the names of <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptists, Quakers,</hi> and <hi>Sectaries;</hi> in meting that measure unto them, which should they mete unto thee, thou wouldest cry out of, as most injurious, and unjust.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It may not be passed over without observation, how ever and anon (throughout his Pamphlet) he is uttering something in the praise of himself, quite contrary to the advice of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who saith, <hi>Let</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Pro. 27.2.</note>
               <hi>another man praise thee, and not thy own mouth.</hi> He telleth his Reader, that his <hi>habitation is in that Parish and Street, where the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan is</hi> (i. e.) <hi>the Quakers meeting place; though God may have his Antipas where Satan's seat is,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> So that <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> esteemeth himself <hi>Gods Antipas</hi> in James Parish.
<note n="(w)" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>&amp; q. d. vice, seu loce, omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Vel,</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. q. d. Contra omnes.</note> Antipas (if thou understandest Greek) is a name that hath a double signification, either it importeth one that is, <hi>vice omnium,</hi> that is, in the stead or room of all; and so denoteth <hi>excellency</hi> above others; and in that sense thy ambition is to proclaime thy self <hi>Gods Antipas.</hi> Or Antipas signfieth one that is, <hi>conti a omnes;</hi> that is, against all, or contrary to all. As <hi>Antichrist</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth such a one as is contrary to Christ. And in this latter acceptation thou mayest most properly call thy self <hi>Antipas,</hi> that is to say, such a one as art <hi>contrary</hi> to, and most desperatly set against, all of all sects, and professions, except those of thy own brotherhood. Just such an <hi>Ancipas</hi> (as
<note n="(x)" place="margin">Gen. 16.12.</note>
               <hi>Ismael</hi> was) <hi>whose hand is against every man,</hi> that cannot see with <hi>thine</hi> eyes, and believe with <hi>thy</hi> faith, and <hi>every mans hand against thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what's the reason <hi>Will.</hi> that (thy <hi>habitation</hi> being so near the Quakers meeting place) neither thou, nor thy Priest <hi>John Paul</hi> (that I can understand) did ever come to this <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> there, by the force of <hi>truth</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, or confute those <hi>deluded</hi> souls? Though thou hatest
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204995:16"/>their <hi>persons,</hi> yet me-thinks thou should'st shew some pity to them, in endeavouring to save their <hi>souls:</hi> unlesse thy malice be come to the same heighth with that of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, viz.</hi> to wish, and consult the ruine both of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, and soules.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>14</label> In page the (50) he layeth about him what he can, to draw reproach upon the <hi>Quakers,</hi> reciting severall things done, and said, by severall persons, but naming no body; lest his abominable lies should be detected, to the shame of him, and his hypocriticall profession. He putteth down certain letters in his margent, with which severall mens names do begin, and so leaveth it to those that shall read, to fasten the thing spoken, or done, upon whom they please, whose names do begin with such a letter.</p>
            <p>He beginneth thus: <hi>What saith one? do you look to be sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the boy that was born at</hi> Jerusalem? (who this <hi>one</hi> was, his Reader must divine, and conjecture, for he nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no body, lest he should have the lye proved upon him) and then addeth these seeming devout words, <hi>Oh my soul! It's that holy Child Jesus, that these wretches do thus jeere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Observe Reader, if envy hath not consumed the understanding, and quite besotted the minde, of this <hi>blind Pharisee.</hi> One asked (if you will believe him) <hi>Do you look to be saved by the boy that was born at</hi> Jerusalem? and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently (by way of complaint) he telleth his <hi>soul,</hi> that it was <hi>the holy Child Jesus that was jeered</hi> by that question. Why <hi>William?</hi> was the holy Child Jesus born at <hi>Jerusalem?</hi> hast thou never read, or hast thou forgotten, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do testifie that Christ was born at
<note n="(y)" place="margin">Mar. 2.1.</note>
               <hi>Bethlehem?</hi> hast not thou professed Christ for many years past to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, who now at last doest demonstrate thy self to be as great a stranger to the place of his birth, as thou art to his <hi>holy, meek, innocent</hi> life? Have not the Apostles, Saints, Martyrs, and Holy men, now for more then <hi>sixteen hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years</hi> past, preach't and professed, Christ the Son of God born in <hi>Bethlehem?</hi> and doest thou now come to set
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204995:17"/>up a <hi>new</hi> Christ that was <hi>born at Jerusalem?</hi> for, if the <hi>holy Child Jesus</hi> whom thou doest worship, were reproached by that (pretended) question, then it's manifest, that the same whom thou doest so worship, was born at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and consequently is another then the true Christ, who was born in <hi>Bethlehem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou proceedest on, in the same page and sayest, that <hi>some work on the Lords day, water Gardens, dry Clothes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Who are those <hi>some</hi> that do this? <hi>That</hi> the Reader must find out by divination if he can, for here is no body named. But what if <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> himself, be found guilty of that very thing, which he here chargeth upon others as a crime? Will he not then appear with all his feigned pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession, and seeming sanctity, in the sight of all sober, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding men, to be a most <hi>brazen fac't</hi> hypocrite? Then let me ask thee, <hi>Will.</hi> was not thy own hedge hunge with <hi>Cloaths</hi> upon the <hi>second day of May</hi> last past, being the first day of the week? If so, let me further ask thee in the words of the Apostle,
<note n="(z)" place="margin">Rom. 2.21.</note>
               <hi>Thou which teachest another, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est thou not thy self? thou that preachest, a man should not steal, doest thou steal?</hi> &amp;c. thou that wouldst render a people odious for doing so and so, and then cryest out to the Magistrate to persecute them to the death, as persons not fit to be tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated in a Common-wealth, doest thou thy self the <hi>same</hi> thing, which in them thou so zealously condemnest? Art thou he that callest thy self <hi>Gods Antipa's</hi> (in James Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish) and yet found to be such a notorious hypocrite, as this doth demonstrate thee to be? doest thou think because thou mayest haply blind the eyes of some simple men with thy rotten profession, with thy feigned devotion, talking of <hi>Christ, Scriptures, Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. that thou shalt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be able to hide thee, from the all-seeing eye of the Lord God Almighty? Hast thou never read what the porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Hypocrite</hi> will be from the hand of him that is righteous in Judgment? Hear, and consider, and repent of this thy horrible wickednesse, before the wrath of the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204995:17"/>Lord break forth upon thee, and there be none found able to quench it.</p>
            <p>In the same page thou speakest of a <hi>perfect Quaker, that told an honest young man, that he did thank God that he had burned the Bible?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Reader, what <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> doth here assert, thou mayest believe if thou wilt; if thou darest adventure to build thy faith, upon his saying It is so. Here is no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son named, that he might be sure to lye with some kind of safety, in case the person on whom he should fasten that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, should come to make the thing appear to be false. Why had'st thou not named the <hi>perfect Quaker,</hi> and the <hi>honese young man?</hi> that so, either the iniquity of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression might have rested upon the head of the one, or the lye upon the head of the other.</p>
            <p>How many hundred wicked, unclean, abominable, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous expressions, could I recite, that have dropt from the lips of those that are called Presbyters, and are follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Priests, and then cry out, <hi>Oh my soul,</hi> this is the <hi>blessed perfection</hi> of the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and <hi>Priesclings?</hi> These are the fruits of a wicked <hi>toleration,</hi> &amp;? Wouldest not thou, and thy generation laugh me to scorn, and cry out shame of such a sottish, and unequall way of proceeding? What thou wouldest esteem the same thing to be, being found in another, conclude it to be <hi>such,</hi> being found in thy self.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>15</label> In page the (51) <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> inserteth the examination of one <hi>Thomas Peacock:</hi> reciting many wicked, unsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voury expressions that should proceed out of his mouth, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A. But what is this to the <hi>Quakers?</hi> for <hi>Thomas Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> is no more a <hi>Quaker</hi> then <hi>thou</hi> art: being a bitter, professed enemy to them, which hath been sufficiently manifested, by his violent disturbing them, &amp;c. nor do they any more own <hi>him</hi> in his filthinesse, than they do <hi>thee.</hi> For my part, I look upon that spirit by which he is guided, to be as unclean, and filthy, as that which act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th in thee;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204995:18"/>onely with this difference, that his wickednesse is more open, and manifest, in the eyes of all men; and thou hast gotten a covering to thy self, made up of outward professi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, such as they had that cryed, the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> and yet murdered the <hi>Son of God,</hi> of whom that <hi>Temple</hi> was but a figure, and a shadow.</p>
            <p>Before I close this, I cannot but let the Reader see the basenesse, and disingenuity, of this envious mans spirit, who hath raked into severall expressions, and actions, of four, five, six, seaven, or more years standing (long before the name of <hi>Quakers</hi> was heard of in the Nation) and cast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them upon the men of his rage, as if they had been now fresh done, and spoken; and then saith, These be your <hi>perfect Quakers,</hi> and this is <hi>their blessed perfection.</hi> By which disingenuous way of proceeding, <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> may throw off all <hi>Davids Psalmes</hi> and say, what? <hi>David</hi> talk of the <hi>Law of the Lord,</hi> and of his <hi>testimonies,</hi> and he <hi>a murderer?</hi> he sing of the <hi>blessednesse of the perfect man,</hi> and an <hi>adulterer?</hi> a blessed perfection indeed! And so for <hi>Solomon;</hi> cast off all his sayings; What? he preach of the <hi>fear of the Lord,</hi> and an Idolater? he talk of <hi>just men,</hi> and the <hi>paths of the upright,</hi> and a follower of strange women? And hence proceed to trample upon <hi>Pauls</hi> Epistles, and say, what? he write to others of the <hi>grace of Christ,</hi> and the <hi>love</hi> of Christ, and he one that <hi>crucified</hi> him? he talk of speaking <hi>wisdome among them that are perfect,</hi> and he a persecutor of the Saints? <hi>a blessed perfection indeed?</hi> Just as if, what a man had <hi>once</hi> been, he must needs <hi>alwayes</hi> be: and so should never come to witnesse washing, and cleansing from his former wickednesse; and though he be washed, and cleans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and through the power of Gods grace be turned to the Lord, yet the filthynesse of his former conversation must be raked together, and made matter of reproach to him, and the truth he witnesseth; and to all those, that have been made partakers of the same grace with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>16</label> Another peece of the wretchednesse of his viperous spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204995:18"/>is seen in his taking some <hi>particular</hi> action of a person that's called <hi>a Quaker,</hi> and making it to be the proper effect of the <hi>principles,</hi> and also concluding it to be the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise;</hi> of all that are called by that name, whereas, there were in all ages such as had <hi>a forme of godlinesses,</hi> but <hi>denyed the power thereof:</hi> and yet that was no just ground of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, to those that stood in the power of godlinesse? In <hi>Pauls</hi> dayes, there were <hi>false Apostles,</hi> but yet, that could not be charged to the account of those that were <hi>true.</hi> And at this day, I do believe that there are many persons of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean spirits, that shelter themselves under the name of <hi>Quakers</hi> (just as <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> doth under the name of a Zealous <hi>Antipas</hi>) whose wickednesse shall be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest, and their uncleannesse discovered, by which many of the enemies of the truth shall be <hi>hardned,</hi> and <hi>stumble,</hi> and <hi>fall,</hi> to their own destruction.</p>
            <p>The question is not, Whether a man or woman that is called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> did not do this, or that, particular wicked action? (for many turning from the Lord, may turn his <hi>grace into wantonnesse,</hi> and proceed on to <hi>deny the Lord that bought them</hi>): but the question is, whether that the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> of the people called Quakers, do allow of such <hi>practises?</hi> and whether the body, or society, of that people do <hi>own</hi> such, or such, particular persons, that are found guilty of such particular evils? Thou thyself sayest in page the (44) of thy Pamphlet; <hi>We must first enquire what the principles are that such do hold out,</hi> alleadging this as the reason, <hi>for</hi> (sayest thou) <hi>if they hold out sound principles in doctrine, that such things ought not to be done, then cannot these things be justly charged on them.</hi> Now then, what are those <hi>principles</hi> of the Quakers, that do hold forth liberty to the flesh? or what are those particular evil persons, or practises, that thou canst charge them with owning, or countenancing?</p>
            <p>Thou sayest, thou livest near the Quakers meeting-place; why then doest thou not there appear, and shew what <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple</hi> they hold forth that leadeth to uncleanness, in life and conversation; and what particular evil deed, or evil doer,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204995:19"/>they do there own among them? untill thou hast done which, blush and be ashamed (if there be yet any thing left in thee that can blush) to take the words, or works, of any <hi>particular</hi> person that is called a <hi>Quaker,</hi> to make them matter of reproach, to the principles, and practises, of that whole people, who in principle, and practise do dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own all that, which stand th not in the fear of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sect. </seg>17</label>
               <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> having vomited up the ranchour of his vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous spirit, railing at one, reviling another, and casting dirt upon a third, he cometh in page (54) to make a high encomium in praise of his <hi>godly, able</hi> Ministers, for <hi>bearing their testimony to the truth of Jesus Chrict, and to their solemn league, and covenant, and against the errors, heresies, and blasphemies of the times, &amp;c.</hi> and then telleth his <hi>Brethren</hi> (in persecution) that <hi>what ever others do, he doth look upon them as the Chariots of</hi> Israel, <hi>and the Horse-men thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I presume the people of England would gladly be rid of such <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>Horse-men:</hi> that serve for little else then to tread them down, and trample upon them, as morter in the Streets: that make it their businesse to <hi>oppresse a man and his</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 2.2.</note>
               <hi>house, even a man and his heritage;</hi> vexing and suing them at the law for the tenth of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, tearing the bread from between the teeth of the needy, to satisfie their unsatiable lusts. Are they Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of Christ, that take a man by the throat, dragge him from his family, and cast him into some nasty prison, or dungeon, for the tithe of his <hi>Corne, Calves, Geese, Apples, Eggs?</hi> &amp;c.Thou that seemest to be such a zealous advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate for the Scripture, search, and see if thou canst find any Ministers of Christ there, that were ever found in the shape of <hi>Wolves,</hi> worrying Christs <hi>Lambs</hi> under the name of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Blasphemers;</hi> that cryed out to the powers of the earth; to whip, imprison, persecute, and destroy the innocent, to whose charge they have nought to lay, nor whereof they may accuse them, save only in the <hi>matters of their God,</hi> Such <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the greatest part of those whom thou callest the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>of</hi> Israel, <hi>and the Horsemen thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:204995:19"/>
            <p> And now I am come to <hi>Will. Grigg's master-peece</hi> of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednesse, and such a peece it is, that I want expressions to let the Reader see the length, breadth, and depth thereof. It beginneth in the close of page (55) where he telleth his Reader, that <hi>upon the fifth of</hi> Febuary 1656, <hi>one</hi> Lewis Harris <hi>a Quaker having been in the Country, came home to his house in</hi> Bristoll, <hi>and there meets with one</hi> Will. Hill <hi>a brother of that Friery.— These, discoursing of their pure Religion, Ranting, and Quaking, at last their words came to blows, and</hi> Harris <hi>murders</hi> Hill; <hi>for which murder he was arraigned, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and executed. Thus</hi> (saith he) <hi>having such wicked principles, they both came to this untimely, and shamefull end.</hi> He further saith, that this <hi>Harris, had a Letter from some Quakers, which he, when he was upon the Gallowes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed to a Godly Minister there attending,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Minister having received it, tore it presently in peeces, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> which some <hi>Quakers that were there present, said, what? will ye persecute to the death? Thus</hi> (saith he) <hi>calling this just execution for murder, persecution.</hi> And then closeth with this seeming pious Query; <hi>And my brethren, is not this also to be bewailed, that such liberty should be given to a people of such principles, who would not have murderers executed, but call it persecution?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Here is such a compacted peece of Villainous fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood, such a huddle of lyes couch't together, to render the truth of God, and it's friends odious, as the like I have seldom met with. Here is the Prince of darknesse coming forth from under an outward profession of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and displaying himself in his proper colours. Who, but he that is the <hi>father of lies,</hi> and was <hi>a lyar from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning,</hi> could prompt, and prevaile with, a seeming <hi>zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Pharisee,</hi> to invent, print, and publish such monstrous lyes as these, hoping thereby to draw the people of his rage, into contempt and hatred with the powers of the earth?</p>
            <p>Whereas first he saith that those two men were <hi>Quakers,</hi> it's sufficiently known to be a notorious lye. Unlesse he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204995:20"/>will needs have them to be Quakers, because one of them was sometimes seen at the Quakers meetings: whither many scores of persons have been often seen to resort, of purpose to scoffe, scorne, and revise them. <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> would esteem it a very injurious way of proceeding, should every drunkard, swearer, scoffer, and unclean person, that cometh to near in <hi>James Steeple</hi> house, be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>one</hi> with him, and of his fellowship, because they some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times frequent the same publick place of hearing, whither all may come that will. And as a proof of what I have afferted, the Reader may know, that <hi>Harris</hi> who dyed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tree, was so far from being a Quaker, that he was not wash't from his open prophannesse, as drunkennesse, swearing, &amp;c. And as for <hi>Hill</hi> (who was the person mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered) he had so little relation to the Quakers, that he was a scoffer, and derider of them. And particularly, not many months before he was slain, meeting with a person (that's called a Quaker) to whom he had been but a little time before a servant, did openly in <hi>Maryport Street</hi> in <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoll,</hi> with words of scorne, jeere and scoffe at him. And yet these two persons must needs be <hi>Quakers,</hi> that thereby that wicked fact, committed by the one in murdering the other, might the better be fastned, as a staine, and a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, upon all that are called by that name. Thus much I had not spoken touching the
<note n="*" place="margin">De mortuis nil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nisi neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sarium.</note> dead, but that necessity constrained me for the vindication of the truth.</p>
            <p>In this and many other particulars in his Book, <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> dealeth with the people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> as that wicked generation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with the Christians, in the daies of <hi>Nero</hi> the <hi>Tyrant</hi> (viz.) when ever any horrible wickedness, and Villainy was committed by their own associates, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently they cry out, The <hi>Christians,</hi> The <hi>Christians,</hi> and then proceed on sorely to punish, and torture them.</p>
            <p>His wickednesse is yet further manifested, in what he saith touching the <hi>letter,</hi> and what was spoken upon <hi>the tearing it in peeces.</hi> For the truth of the thing was this. This <hi>Harris</hi> and a woman that was to suffer with him for
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:204995:20"/>the like offence, drawing near their end, it was earnestly desired by some of both their relations, that some certain persons of those called <hi>Quakers</hi> might come to converse with them; and accordingly, three of them came to the prison, but were denyed accesse to them: upon which one of them made her application to one of the then
<note n="†" place="bottom">I leave it to <hi>John Harper</hi> (to whose soul I wish much good) in the fear of God to consider, whether it be not the heighth of cruelty, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dying per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons liberty to converse, touching the eternall state of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious souls.</note> Sheriffs: who most injuriously, and contrary to all rules of Charity, and equity, did refuse to let her come to them. Whereupon those three persons writt a letter, directed to them both, <hi>to mind them of their condition,</hi> and <hi>exhort them to turn to the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. in which, among other expressions, this was one. (viz.) <hi>We having sought many wayes to come at you (but have been hindred by the wickednesse of those, who have not learned to do as they would be done by) and now waiting under our burdens, have liberty of the Lord to write these lines unto you both, as unto one, being</hi> (mark) <hi>in one bond of INIQUITY, and so under one JUDGMENT.</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> By which it's evident to all whose eyes malice hath not stop't, that these people, being Quakers, were so far from esteeming the execution of these murderers, <hi>persecution,</hi> that they write to them in expresse termes, as to evil doers, and such as for their evil deeds were under one, and the same <hi>just</hi> sentence.</p>
            <p>Well, <hi>Harris</hi> carryeth this letter with him to the place of Execution, and being upon the tree, he casteth it among the people, desiring it might be handed to <hi>Ralph Farmer</hi> (that blood-thirsty Priest) who opened, and lookt on it, and so tore it in peeces; telling the people he had received <hi>a lying, and scandalous paper, signed by some Quakers,</hi> &amp;c. Whereupon a
<note n="†" place="bottom">Edward Erbery.</note> young man standing by, called to him and said, <hi>Ralph Farmer, thou had'st done well, to have read it to the people, that they might have judged wherein the lying, and slanders did appear, or else it will stand upon thy head as a witnesse against thee.</hi> So that, he spake never a word touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>persecuting to the death,</hi> nor was there ought said by him; nor any other, touching <hi>murder,</hi> which might give so much as a shadow of occasion to this horrible, vile, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:204995:21"/>false suggestion. And yet he is not ashamed to say that some Quakers did expresly call that <hi>just execution for mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, persecution.</hi> And then asketh his <hi>brethren, whether this also be not to be bewailed, that such liberty should be given to a people of such principles, who would not have murderers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted, but call it persecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having layd severall lyes for his foundation, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lished it to the world that the Quakers said so, and so, which was never said, nor entered into their hearts to speak: now he cometh to make his <hi>murderous</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, from his hellish premises: <hi>Ergo,</hi> no liberty for such persons. First forge a thing as spoken by <hi>a single</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and then making that (pretended) saying to be the principle of <hi>all</hi> the Quakers, and from thence proceed to sentence them as not worthy to share in that liberty to which they are borne.</p>
            <p>Let all that fear the Lord, or have any sobriety left in them, judge what maner of person this is, who talketh with such seeming devotion of God, Christ, <hi>his</hi> Jesus, <hi>his</hi> Saviour, &amp;c. and yet thus manifestly publish himself to be one who is a forger of lyes, and maketh no conscience of speaking any thing, printing, and publishing any thing, though never so false, and slanderous; so as that he may disgorge himself of that inveterate malice, he beareth in his brest, against those to whose charge he hath little to lay, save what he is constrained to consult with the accuser of the brethren, to create and invent.</p>
            <p>And to you that are his <hi>brethren</hi> in <hi>Bristoll,</hi> I have this to say: I will not deal by you, as he doth with those against whom he casteth 'out his darts <hi>(viz.)</hi> cry out and say, loe here is your Religion, and so cast his wickednesse upon all your heads. I shall not say, It's <hi>your</hi> principle to lye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause your Brother <hi>Grigge</hi> doth demonstrate it to be his by his practise; nor will I say, that this his horrible iniquity is the proper effect of that Religion which you all professe. I have better thoughts of many of you, and may yet live to see you redeemed from among the persecutors, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyers,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:204995:21"/>to lye down in the flock among the Lambs of Christ.</p>
            <p>But if what <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> hath here, and in many other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Book, brought forth, be indeed the fruits that natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally flow from what you professe, and you own them as such; let me tell you that your root is accursed, and your vine is <hi>the vine of Sodom;</hi> and unlesse he and you be by Repentance trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted and grafted into the <hi>true vine Christ Jesus,</hi> who is truth it self, and no head to lyars; who is meek and lowly, and no friend to the envious and haughty ones; who is full of love and tendernesse, and no friend to persecutors; you shall no more see the face of God with comfort, than those evil <hi>Angels</hi> which he <hi>hath reserved unto everlasting Chaines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude v. 6.</note>
               <hi>under darknesse, unto the judgment of the great day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to thee <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> I say for close of this: whereas thou sayest positively that it is the Quakers <hi>principle,</hi> that they would not have <hi>murderers executed, but call it persecution.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less thou shalt send it under thy hand to the Quakers meeting-place (near to which thou livest) that such a person, or such persons by name, that are of their society, and communion, are of that principle; or thou come there and charge them face to face, and prove it; blush and be ashamed, lay thy hand upon thy mouth, and let it be henceforth stopt, from casting out such odious slanders, and false accusations, upon a people who do in heart and tongue deny any such principle as that. The Quakers principle is, that God is righteous, and so are all his Statutes; and he hath said that <hi>who so sheddeth mans blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9.6.</note>
               <hi>by man shall his blood be shed.</hi> Which Statute they own, and assent to, as <hi>holy, just,</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> and such as shall fall on the head of the murderer (as an evil doer) throughout all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>And now Reader, (thou that art not drunk with prejudice against the truth) behold and see: what wickednesse is not this man ready to act, who is of such a seared conscience, as that he can feigne words to be spoken by persons who never spoke them, and assert that which was never spoken, to be the <hi>principle</hi> of a whole people, of set purpose that he might (if possible) have the blood, and the lives of those, whom other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise he cannot present justly culpable to the Magistrate?</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:204995:22"/>
            <p> Had this man been living among his Brethren the Pharisees in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> would he have stuck to have borne false witnesse against the Son of God? nay for as much as he hath done it to his members, hath he not done it already to the Head?</p>
            <p>In page (49) of his Pamphlet, he calleth those persons <hi>filthy dreamers, Inchanters, and Sorcerers,</hi> who <hi>speak and say,</hi> look to the light within you; but well, and happy, were it for him, if he turned to that pure light of Christ within them, which would lead him out of lying, slandering, and false accusing: that he might witnesse washing, and cleansing, from his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent pollution, before the terrible day of the Lord overtake him, in which the lyar and the false accuser, the envious man (who is a murderer) and the persecutor, shall call and cry <hi>to the mountaines</hi> and to the <hi>rocks,</hi> to cover them from the wrath of the <hi>Lamb,</hi> and they shall not be able.</p>
            <p>In page (56) and (57) he falleth to sporting himself,
<note place="margin">Sect. 18.</note> telling a story of <hi>Lambeth fair,</hi> and <hi>of a Market</hi> since set up called <hi>Toleration,</hi> and (just like a fool in a play) faineth a man to come to <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> for such a Book, and then for such a Book; and then answereth himself, what his foolish fancy suggesteth: In which paths of his folly, and lightnesse, it's not my purpose to spend time to follow him. Only in passing along, I must ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Reader, what the designe of the man is in all that he saith, touching the sale of those severall Books, he demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> (viz.) to enveigh against liberty of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to any save to himself, and his imperious generation. <hi>They</hi> must have liberty to Preach any thing and Print any thing, and all others must stand by like dumb pictures, and be content to be painted in what monstrous, and ugly shape soever, their malice pleaseth to present them to the worlds view. They would have liberty (as dread soveraigns to all other professors) to impeach whom they please for <hi>hereticks,</hi> and <hi>blasphemers,</hi> and proceed on to execute them as such, and yet stop the mouthes, and blind the hands of the accused that so they might have no liberty to defend, or make a just plea for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; Just as if a company of lawlesse persons should meet <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> in the Streets of <hi>Br<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>stoll,</hi> and should lay hold of him, and tie his hands behind him, and stop his mouth, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:204995:22"/>fall to beating of him; and cry out, A thief, a thief. And if any Magistrate should passe by, and say to those wicked ones, forbear, and let him speak for himself, that I may see if he be indeed guilty of that whereof you accuse him; and they should yet continue to stop his mouth, and beat him, crying out, <hi>A thief, a thief;</hi> Whether would not <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in <hi>Bristoll</hi> esteem this to be (as indeed it is) most injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and wicked dealing? there is no difficulty in making the application.</p>
            <p>In page the (60) <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> hath this expression.
<note place="margin">Sect. 19.</note>
               <hi>Though liberty in it self be a good thing, yet it's weaklings temptation, and seducers advantage. And</hi> (saith he) <hi>I am sure it hath sadly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved so, and that to the TEARING TO PIECES of God and Christ, and all that is, and should be dearer to us then our very lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> What? <hi>tear God in pieces? tear Christ in pieces?</hi> tear truth in pieces? Oh horrid blasphemy! what cursed tongue, of man or Devil, could utter more dreadfull blasphemy, against the pure name of the Lord God Almighty, and Jesus Christ his Son, who is one with him, than this is? what? a God over all blessed for ever, and yet be torn in <hi>pieces?</hi> A Christ, by <hi>whom the world was made,</hi> and yet be torne in <hi>pieces?</hi> what is this but blasphemously to make the immortall God, like unto the heathens
<note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 4.5.</note>
               <hi>Dagon,</hi> which <hi>fell before the Arke of the Lord,</hi> and was broken in pieces? what's this but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that God, who created all things by the <hi>word of his power,</hi> to be no God, but to be subject to Creatures, the works of his own hands? For, that which must tear God in <hi>pieces,</hi> must be stronger than God, and must be before him: and consequently he is no God; for, he is not God, before whom there was another, and than whom there is a mightier to be found. Let me ask <hi>Will. Grigge,</hi> what he asketh his <hi>brethren</hi> in page (52) of his Pamphlet, <hi>whose hair is not an end, and heart trembling, to hear such horrid filthynesse, and unheard of blasphemy,</hi> as this? Art thou the man that did'st thirst after the blood of <hi>James Naylor,</hi> as a <hi>blasphemer,</hi> and still doest thirst after the blood of the people called Anabaptists, Quakers, and other Sectaries, (as thou callest them) as <hi>blasphemers;</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:204995:23"/>and yet thou thy self found uttering such dreadfull blasphemies against the very <hi>being</hi> of the everlasting God, and against his dear Son Jesus Christ, as will make the ears of any sober hearer to tingle? Cease, thou cursed speaker, to utter thy lies, and thy blasphemies, and be silent before the great God, who is <hi>one,</hi> and his <hi>name one,</hi> and cannot be torn in <hi>pieces</hi> (as thou blasphemously affirmest), but will himself <hi>turn all the wicked into hell,</hi> and such as forget to speak reverently of his glorious name.</p>
            <p>I had now done with <hi>Will. Grigg's Lambeth fair,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sect. 20.</note> and his Market called <hi>Toleration</hi> also? but that I may not omitt the observation of an expression that he hath touching <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> of <hi>Bristoll,</hi> speaking of whom in page (60) he notifies him in his margent with this passage, <hi>(viz.) This man</hi> (saith he) <hi>being a schollar; I heartily desire that he may not carry about him his learning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam 11.7.</note>
               <hi>and parts, as</hi> Uriah <hi>did</hi> David, <hi>letters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> I know but one <hi>letter</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> that <hi>Ʋriah</hi> carryed, which was to <hi>Joah,</hi> whilest he was laying siege to <hi>Rabbah:</hi> which letter he so carryed, as that by reason thereof he had his own throat cut. So that <hi>Will. Grigge</hi> doth fairly caution <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Speed</hi> that he meet not with the same end from the hands of the Priests (for against their wickednesse is his contention) with his <hi>learning, and parts,</hi> that <hi>Uriah</hi> did with <hi>Davids letter:</hi> Which caution doth very well suit with what <hi>Thomas Speed</hi> had offered him by a Priest, as they travelled upon the high way together; which the Reader may take in this brief relation following, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sometime after the name of Quaker came forth in this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<note place="margin">He had many gray haires.</note>
               <hi>Tho: Speed</hi> tiding upon the high-way, overtook a grave Priest of <hi>Summerset shire;</hi> with whom (after much commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication betwixt them) he was engaged in a dispute touching the Priest's call to the Ministery by Bishops, his preaching for a forced maintenance,
<note place="margin">☞</note> &amp;c. neither of which the Priest being able to maintain by the Scripture, he was so hard put to it, that he began to fly to evasions, and slatly to deny what he had just before asserted; Whereupon <hi>Tho. Speed</hi> soberly cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned him, that he should take heed he did not lye; for that he had said so, and so, but just before: At which the Priest
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:204995:23"/>was so exceedingly enraged that (having in his hand a clubb much bigger than the men of his coate usually carry about them) he puts spurrs to his Horse (as they were both riding on <hi>Mendip-hill</hi>) and most fiercely made at him, and in all probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity had not <hi>Tho. Speed</hi> espied him in his approach and avoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, he had struck him off his horse, to the endangering of his life. But seeing he could not have his will on him with his hands, he fell to it with his tongue, calling him <hi>Rogue, Dog, Villaine, Jesuite,</hi> with as many other names of reproach, as he could possibly invent; and so continued raving, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, for two miles together: Although <hi>Tho. Speed</hi> in sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse reasoned with him, and told him, that <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> who were Ministers of Christ, were no <hi>Strikers,</hi> nor <hi>Revilers,</hi> nor did they use to assault men on the high way, striving to maintain that by the power of the <hi>clubb,</hi> which they could not do by the power of <hi>truth.</hi> Notwithstanding all which, the fiercenesse of the Priest was nothing allayed, but so inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate was his rage and madnesse, that as they both came near to <hi>Stepton malliard,</hi> he told <hi>Tho. Speed</hi> in expresse words, that <hi>he</hi> (the said <hi>Tho. Speed</hi>) <hi>had rode in danger of his life, in riding with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How suitable <hi>Will. Grigg's</hi> caution is to this Priest's practise, and how safe <hi>Tho. Speeds</hi> life would be, were it not kept in His hands who ruleth the World, let all that are sober judge.</p>
            <p>The three last leaves of <hi>Will. Griggs</hi> Pamphet, are filled most with passionate exclamations; and bitter invectives, against liberty of conscience, under the name of <hi>a sad toleration:</hi> with which he intermingleth what arguments he can possibly offer, to instigate and perswade, those in authority, to make laws of <hi>restraint,</hi> and to <hi>compell people</hi> (as he expresseth himself in page (65) <hi>to ordinances though unwillingly, that so they may be brought to God and goodnesse willingly.</hi> As if it were in the power of man by any externall force, to make men believe what they present to them as truth. Hath this blind Pharisee never read the Scriptures (of which he doth so much talk) that saith <hi>The</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">John 3.8.</note>
               <hi>wind bloweth where it listeth,</hi> and that
<note n="†" place="bottom">John 8.44.</note>
               <hi>none can come unto Christ, except the Father draw him;</hi> and yet he would have men brought to God by outward violence?</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:204995:24"/>
            <p> Can the clubb without, beget faith within? can any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward law change the heart, because it might be of force to tie the hands? The temporall sword may hurry men into the common fold of professing hypocrites, and cause them (through fear) to professe that with their lips, which in their hearts they deny: but to prevaile with a man, to turn to the Lord with all his heart, nothing is, or can be, of force, but the grace, and spirit, of Him that made him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William,</hi> I know thy designe, and thy root is discerned by its fruits: faine would'st thou have the Magistrates to be dab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the blood of those, whom the spirit that is in thee <hi>(that lusteth to envy)</hi> would not have to live by thee upon the earth. But to them, and thee, I say, Take heed and beware what ye do. Better were it <hi>that a milstone were hanged about your necks, and ye cast into the bottome of the sea,</hi> then that ye <hi>should offend one of Christs little ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And think not to say with your selves, when the Lord shall come to make inquisition for blood, that ye have sought the blood of none but <hi>hereticks,</hi> and <hi>blasphemers.</hi> Remember that the Prophets of the Lord of old were stoned, and slain, not as true, but as false.</p>
            <p>Christ himself was crucified, not as a good man, but as <hi>a blasphemer</hi> and <hi>a deceiver;</hi> and the spirit that slew him was as high in outward profession, as ye are or can be. The disciples and Apostles of Christ after him, were put to death not as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and righteous, but as <hi>hereticks,</hi> and deluders of the people; and that by those who were devout, who walked much more blamelesse in the eyes of men, than thou doest or canst walk. <hi>Saul's</hi> conversation (even whilst he wash't his hands in Christs blood) was far cleaner then thine; therefore think not that thy outward profession shall save thee from the hand of the righteous God. Thou art now doing <hi>Sauls</hi> work, and unlesse thou come to witnesse his change by turning to the Lord, against whom thou art found <hi>fighting,</hi> thou shalt no more enter into the Kingdome of God, then those high pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing Jews that murdered the Son of God, and afterwards turned not to him by repentance. Remember that thou art warned now in thy life time, and though thou mayest spurn at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:204995:24"/>it now in the day of thy health; yet know, when the day of calamity shall overtake thee, when thou shalt come to lye down upon thy <hi>bed of sorrow,</hi> when the <hi>book</hi> of records shall be opened, and Gods witnesse shall come to speak, with sigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and tears shalt thou then cry out, and wish. Oh that in the day of my visitation, I had minded the things that did <hi>concerne my peace!</hi> but now (alas!) <hi>they are did from mine eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall now close all with an addition of a few particulars touching persecution, which I do (in truth of love to their souls) offer to the serious consideration, of all Magistrates throughout the world, that professe the name of Christ.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The first blood that ever was shed in the world was shed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Religious</hi> score, and consideration. <hi>Cain</hi> was the first per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutor, who <hi>slew his</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 4.4, 5, 8.</note>
               <hi>Brother</hi> Abel, because the Lord had <hi>regard to him and his offering,</hi> but to <hi>Cain</hi> and his <hi>offering</hi> the Lord had not <hi>regard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Whosoever he be, Magistrate or other, that shall imprison, scourge, or put to death, any man, for things barely relating to the worship of God, or the profession of his name; that man or Magistrate, doth tread in the steps of <hi>Cain</hi> the first persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: and (without repentance) shall receive his reward. <hi>Cain</hi> slew not <hi>Abel</hi> as a transgressor of the Law, that bindeth the outward man; because he had hurt him in his name, offered violence to his person, or spoiled him of any part of his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward estate, but for that onely which did barely relate to the worship of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The Prophets of the Lord in all ages, were evilly intreated, scourged, imprisoned, and put to death by others; but were themselves never found to scourge, imprison, put to death, or to attempt the doing either of them to any, that professed not faith in that God, whom they served, barely for that cause.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
               <hi>You</hi> cannot be more confident, that you do acceptable ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice unto the Lord, in scourging, imprisoning, and putting to death any men at this day, under the notion of <hi>deceivers,</hi> and <hi>blasphemers;</hi> then the strict, religious, devour Jews were, in crucifying Christ under the same notions: who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing such their judgment of him) was <hi>holy, innocent,</hi> and had wrought nothing worthy of <hi>bonds,</hi> or of <hi>death.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:204995:25"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Should we admitt (which may not be admitted) that the power of punishing error, is committed to the civil sword; yet, he that will undertake to inflict punishment upon the person of any man, upon the account of his erring from the truth, in faith, or profession; must himself first have the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible</hi> knowledge of the mind of God, or else he cannot know when the other erreth from it: and so may strike at the truth, instead of error, and (with the Jews) draw innocent blood upon his own head. And which of you durst to say, you have this <hi>infallible</hi> knowledge of Gods minde?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Who ever he be, Migistrate or other, that doth punish, or destroy the person of any man, for his doing, or not doing that thing, about which his conscience may be exercised, and through the tendernesse of which he may do, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse to do, that particular thing; that man or Magistrate doth committ a <hi>rape</hi> upon that mans conscience, and may in so doing <hi>destroy</hi> him, <hi>for whom Christ dyed:</hi> And wo to him, whom the Lord at his coming, shall find <hi>so</hi> doing.</p>
            <p>Lastly, Christ who was <hi>infallible,</hi> and his Apostles who had the <hi>infallible</hi> spirit, did meet with <hi>Pharisees, Sadduces, false Apostles,</hi> and <hi>false Christs:</hi> whom they did not onely suppose, but infallibly knew, to be <hi>hereticks, deceivers,</hi> and <hi>blasphemers:</hi> and yet it's no where upon record in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that either He, or his Apostles, did at any time cry out to the Magistrate, to punish, or put to death any, in any of the said Sects, as <hi>erronious.</hi> Nor did they threaten them with any such punishment, but left them to have their <hi>inward</hi> Ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to be healed by an <hi>inward</hi> plaister, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the power of truth, and the spirit of the living God; which onely are able to reach the heart, which must first be turned from error unto truth, from sin unto God, before the conformity of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man findeth any acceptance.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>Errata,</hi> Page 18. line 16. for persecuted read prosecuted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:204995:25"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>